You have an animation and you actually want to change the timing of that animation or you want to change some poses and
Kind of offset the animations as if it was an animation layer
This is the kind of functions we take for granted in all our 3d animation package and even in most of our game engines
But once upon a time it was actually a paper
Hi, I'm Jerome and today we'll be looking at the motion warping paper from 1995.
The motion warping paper takes as an idea that you actually have a bunch of curves that
represent animation and it would treat all of those curves separately and then from there
you could actually change those curves to tweak your animation.
So let's see how it was done and how we could implement this in NumPy.
So basically I will import as usual all my libraries and my viewer and I will import
my character and I will duplicate it so I get several characters so I can render several
characters back to next to each other that make my life easier when I would want to show
different options.
And what I would do is actually just load one animation and I will load the file and
support animation from the LaFan animation set.
And from this animation, what I would do is that I will extract two different poses at
the end of the animation.
So you see I'm taking a pose A at frame 695 and one at 92,000 frames.
And then I will only use a small range of the animation, so only 500 frames of animations
that I'm interested in inside of this bigger animation.
So this is the animation I've kept, and so you could see it's just basically a guy dancing
on one foot and giving some kicks on one side and then coming back on the other side.
So that's the animation I will use and that's what I want to tweak, where I want to change
the timing and I want to change the pose and all that kind of stuff.
So just to represent the fact that the paper is talking about a bunch of curves, I would
display here one of the numerous curves that I have on the characters.
So basically I'm picking the quaternions of the left up leg of this character and you
could see so that's the four different values scalar of that quaternion so I
get my w x y z so already just one rotation is four different curves for
one for one bone and then I have that for all the bones and so what the the
paper is basically saying is that you could warp your animation using two
two different functions, and the two different functions
that they do, so they warp the motion curves
with defined by two functions.
And basically what they said, they said that the new curve
will be a function of t, and that function of t,
that new curve will be a function of the original functions
at time t, and then they also say that the time t
is defined as a function of the original times.
So they warp T prime to T in that order.
Basically what they say in this paper,
they say that it's easier to say,
my new animation will have frames
that go from zero to 100, for instance,
and I will want to map frame zero
with the original frame, frame 50, for instance,
with frame 60 of my old animation, original animation,
and frame 100 might be frame 200 of my original animation.
So that's the functions I want to do
to map the time differently.
And then they have the functions
to map the pose differently.
And I will start from the timing function
because it's easier to assume only one dimension, let's say.
And what they say, the inside of the paper,
that basically you give a bunch of keyframes saying that's the time inside of animations
at the time inside of my old animation. And you need a smooth functions to interpolate
those values. And the smooth function they use is the cardinal spline. They basically
says that you could use any type of spline, but they went for the cardinal spline. So
I will do the same. I will use the cardinal spline. So what I have is, as in the paper,
I basically have new time, old time keyframes.
So at frame zero, I want to be at frame zero inside
of my old animation.
At 40, 40, at 100, I want to be at frame 190.
So I want to speed up quite a lot.
And then I will slow it back down,
saying that at the end, at frame 430,
I will only be at frame 400 inside of the animation.
So I will not even reach the end of the animation
with my new animation.
So that's the key frames I will have.
And basically, I picked the functions from the spline theory
papers that videos have made.
So I will just reuse the same functions,
so that the one that converts the cardinal spline to Hermit,
and then how to compute an Hermit spline.
So I will have the Hermit function
so that I can directly use to do my mapping.
And now, basically what I would do
is just use the Amid functions
to convert the different points into a curve.
So we could see what is the mapping
I actually want to do for the timing.
And so this is the mapping I have.
So basically that's the new keyframes
I will be generating for my animation.
So from frame zero to frame 430.
And then we can see the corresponding frame
I will go and pick inside of the original animation.
So I will have at frame zero,
I will be picking the frame zero at frame 100,
see nearly at frame 200.
That's what I was saying.
200, we are on 250s and so on and so on.
So that's the mapping that the curves allows me
to have between my new frames and my old frames.
The only issue I have with this kind of curves
that every time I will want to request the values
at a specific frame for my new animation,
I will have to go and find the corresponding values
inside of the AmidCurve to find where I'm supposed
to be here and then where I will be at the end.
So it's not really user friendly to use the AmidCurve
directly this way.
And what I will do is that I will resample
this pyramid curve now for every frame down here.
So basically, I would say now I know that
between this point and the other points
that I put here at frame 100, I have 100 frames.
So I will compute 100 different values.
So I get the perfect mapping and so on
for every points along my entire curve.
So that's what the resampling is doing here.
So, it re-samples a curve that you're given, so it will give you as many frames as the
frames you're supposed to get here, so that's the re-sample functions.
And to show you what it means to take this Aermid curve and regenerate a new curve using
that re-sample, basically gives me this now.
I still have the curves as it was designed, but now I have for every keyframe in my new animation
I have a direct mapping to where I want to be in the old one
So I don't have to I don't have to compute anything down here now anymore
I can just say hey, I'm computing frame one. What is the value? I'm computing frame 10
What is the value and so on and so on so it's basically becoming a big lookup table
Which makes my life easier when I want to execute more code after that
So now that I know that I want to be able to compute this kind of curves with a linear spacing for all my functions, for all my frames,
basically I will write those functions so I can reuse them and that's what those two functions are.
I have the build curve is the one that generates these curves.
basically saying, if you give me a bunch of keyframes that are going onto an
omit, I will re-sample that values to give you now a mapping between for
every frames and that values. So that's what the build curve does. So it creates
this mapping. And then the warp curve is actually the real functions now. It's the
one that you want to use if you want to warp a data using that curve just generated here.
So the time warp tells you what is the data for every frame and this one allows you to go into
that curve and modify the curve. So basically the only thing it does it looks inside a curve.
so if the time warp said you're supposed to look at frame 10 it goes inside of the curve
looks at the value for the value for that frame 10 and so on but then he will do
a linear interpolation between two frames and why is doing that linear interpolation is because now
for instance at frame one at 300 it might tell me that the value here is not a round frame it might
be 300, it might be 300.5. So I do need to do the linear interpretation between frame 200 and frame
201. So that's what the warp curve does. It goes and it picks the two closest frame and do the
linear interpretation between the two and it does it on the entire curve at once and in any
dimensions but the entire curves at once. Let's remember this one. So that's the two functions
I will be reusing every time I try to build a curve or every time I try to warp a curve using
a time warp. And then we could do finally that time warp now. Basically, I can use my build curve
to create the warping curve, that blue one. And then I could use the warp curve to go and look at
all the quaternions of my animations and warp all those curves using the time-waps curves.
So as I said, this function is able to do it on the entire animations, but as in any dimensions.
So basically, it can do it for every bones of the WXYZ of each quaternions. So it does it in one
pass. So it modifies every curves, which means that now I need to normalize those curves because
what happens is that I'm not using a slope here between the quaternions. I'm just
warping every curve separately. So I'm basically breaking the rule that says that my quaternions
need to be a unit quaternion. So I need to renormalize them. So I renormalize all my quaternions and
And then I compute the new curves also for the positions
using the warp curves function.
And so we can display the results.
And basically what you will see is that the yellow,
the white one is playing the normal animation,
and the green one plays the warped animation.
You could see that the beginning,
it was speeding up a lot,
and now it's slowing down to reach that point
at the same time as him.
It does not even reach the end of the animation.
So that's what the time warp was supposed to do.
So basically, I accelerate because I
wanted to be at frame 100.
I wanted him to be already at the same position as frame 190.
And then at frame 350, they had to be back together
at the same time.
and it was slowing down to reach frame 400 at frame 430.
So that's the timing change of the warping functions.
So I have the function that allows me to map a value to another one.
And in this case, the value that I mapped to another one is the time.
And now what we want to do is actually do the pose change.
So do the first part of those functions here, the one that we have here that says that we
change the curve based on a function that would change the curves itself. And what I
will do is again, I will do keyframes. So I will have the frames for which I want to
to change the values.
Those frames are in the original timing.
And for all of those frames,
I will actually give a pose that I want to match at that time.
So basically at frame zero,
what I would say is that I want to have frame zero.
So basically frame zero means at frame zero,
I want the same pose as the pose that you already have.
that frame 190. I want the pose A that extracted at the beginning, remember. Then frame 2 and 20
and 3 and 20, I actually want the animation itself. And then at frame 349, I want the pose B
that extracted earlier. And then again, the two frames coming from the animation itself.
So that's the key frames I want to generate. So basically, it's really,
as if I was doing in 3D software it's I'm doing a layer on top of my animations
and that's the pose I want to put on that layer and to show you all the
different stuff that I'm trying if I don't execute that of course I would not
have my keyframes and so if I show you this so this is the animation that is
playing and what I said is that at frame 190 I think is that the one yep at frame 190 that
would be disposed in the original animation and actually I would want this pose to be visible
instead so I want to correct to modify this pose to be this one at frame 190 and then at frame 350
50 something, 49, 50. When it reaches this pose, instead of having his leg completely
stretched, I want this pose here. So basically, I want to remove entirely the fact that he
lifts the legs up. So that's the two pose that I want to change in the layer. And then
everything else, I want him to play the normal animation with the ease in and ease out because
I have from frame 0s up to frame 200 something here in the middle.
That should be again the normal pose and at the end also.
So that's what I want to do. To do this, what they do in the paper is that they treat every
curves as just curve and they do the mathematics on top. They just do minus and add. What I would
do in my case is knowing that I'm actually working with quaternions. So instead of directly
just working on each curves and computing offsets on the curves, I will
actually compute offsets in the quaternion space directly. So what I will do
is that I will multiply all my keyframes that I have here, all those values, key
frames, I will convert them into enough sets compared to the actual animations
that I want to apply so I will multiply the inverse of all of my animations
with the keyframes so that gives me an offset that gives me how much I want to
modify the original pose compared to with the pose I have and if I so this is
what I compute here so I turn every keyframes as offsets and now basically
what I could do is I could use that same function that I had to map the timing from my new timing
to the original timing. I will use that to map my local offsets inside of the actual new timing
I want to do. So I will build a curve that will give me the amount of offsets I want to apply
on every frame. So this is what I'm doing. So I'm basically going through a build curve
and I will build that curve separately for each wxyz of microtonance and each xyz of my position.
So I need to compute that separately for each curve. And basically, if I display one of the
curve you end up with is this one. You could see that you get a quaternion that frame 0 that
will be the identity so I mean I don't want to change anything and then at frame 190 that's
where my big change happened and then get the identity again no change no change the big change
and so on so and that's the same for every different
and bones I have inside of my system.
So that curve is already the amount offset I want to apply on every bones along the animation.
So I could display that change directly to show you basically what it means now using
just the position warp, one of the pose warps, and so basically you could see that it's already
rotating the head because it knows that it would reach at frame 190, that's the pose I wanted him
to be and that's where I want him to be now, which is the case, and he's already slowly
applying that change along from frame zero up to there slowly happening applying that change
and then quickly it goes back in the right pose and at the end it will also start to not kick
because it's is framing and then because it holds the kick a long time it's starting to slowly
catching up so that's the change in in the pose that I wanted to do basically as offsets compared
to what animation is. And then the final step to complete the paper is to combine both to
say that you want to change the pose and you want to change the timing by saying that instead of
looking at the change in pose inside of the old timing you will do it in the new timing. So you
would basically do the same. You would change the timing and change the pose. So what I'm doing is
is that I take the curve, the offsets I've applied here,
I take that new curve that does all the change
and I also warp it using the time.
And so I can have now something related to the new time
with the new pose.
And you get this, so the green guy will be playing
just the retiming and the blue one will be playing
the retiming plus the change in the pose.
And that's what the motion warping paper was all about.
And as I said, it's something that we take for granted
in all of our software.
But it's always interesting to see how it could be computed
and all the curves that are in the background
to compute that kind of stuff.
It will be used in a lot of different papers after this one,
because most of the time you would want to change timing,
we want to change posts, we want to reach some stuff,
and every single time it's basically this
or something close to this that will be used.
Hope you enjoyed it and see you next time.